Finding Aid for Thomas Francis Papers
Bentley Historical Library
- General Correspondence, 1933-1969; 13.5 linear feet
  - 1966-1969
    - T-Z; include files for: (Box 14)
      - World Health Organization, animal influenza, study of (Box 14)
- Poliomyelitis Vaccine Evaluation Center, 1953-1957; 10.5 linear feet
  Poliomyelitis Vaccine Evaluation Center, 1953-1957 (10.5 linear feet). Although received as part of the Thomas Francis accession, these are the administrative files of the PEC and as such they include files of those other individuals associated with the work of polio vaccine testing. In this category are lab consultant Herbert A. Wenner and members of the statistical division Robert B. Voight and John Napier. Crucial in importance is the subseries - Topical Files - which contains substantive and procedural information about the administration of the polio vaccine testing. Principal headings within this subseries relate to the PEC's relationship with the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, study lab files, and Jonas Salk materials. Smaller subseries detail activities of Francis and the PEC subsequent to the announcement of the Salk polio vaccine. These relate to matters of the production and allocation of the vaccine and may be found in the subseries, Technical Advisory Committee on Poliomyelitis and under Vaccine.
  Only a small portion of the actual patient testing files have come to the library. There are paper records for patients in the states of Texas through Wyoming only. The whereabouts of the remainder of the paper records is uncertain. The Francis collection does include microfilmed records of the entire project so perhaps the originals were discarded following the filming.
  - Establishing documents and letters, 1953-1954
    - Files, 1953-1954 (Box 14)
  - Topical file
    - Accounting [sample], 1954 (Box 14)
    - Blood sample (Box 14)
      (pre and post vaccine blood sample study)
    - Blood samples (Box 14)
    - Communicable Disease Center
      - General (Box 14)
      - Kunin, Calvin (Box 14)
      - Seibert, Richard H., 1 folder, 1 volume (Box 14)
    - Crank letters, etc., 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Epidemic Intelligence Service (Box 14)
      (officer assignments and participation in polio vaccine evaluation program)
    - Evaluation
      - Charts and graphs (Box 14)
      - Final Report (Box 14)
      - Requests for Information (Box 14)
      - Summary Report and Abstract (Box 14)
    - Field Trial
      - Bleedings (Box 14)
      - Inoculation data finalized (Box 14)
      - Inoculation estimates (Box 14)
      - Irregularities (Box 14)
      - Manual of suggested procedures (Box 14)
      - Operational memoranda (Box 14)
    - Form letters, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Forms (Box 14)
    - Francis, Thomas (Box 15)
      - Congratulatory letters to (Box 15)
      - Congratulatory letters from (Box 15)
      - Daily memoranda (Box 15)
      - Gudakunst lecture, "Approaches to the prevention of poliomyelitis" ud1b 1956 (Box 15)
      - Speaking engagements (Box 15)
    - Gamma globulin, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Hawaii (Box 15)
    - Hemphill, F.M. (Box 15)
      (re evaluation of vaccine effectiveness)
    - Lilly and Company (Box 15)
    - Lot reports (Box 15)
    - Meetings, 27 folders (Box 15)
      (arranged chronologically)
    - National Institutes of Health (Box 15)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis
      - General (Box 15)
      - Dated correspondence, 1954-1955; 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Alphabetical correspondence
        - Dublin, Thomas D (Box 16)
        - Engelbach, Albert G (Box 16)
        - Kumm, Henry W (Box 16)
        - O'Connor, Basil (Box 16)
        - Public Relations (Box 16)
          (Stegen and Graff)
        - Van Riper, Hart E (Box 16)
      - Memoranda (Box 16)
    - Orthopedic Advisors meeting, July 16, 1955 (Box 16)
    - Orthopedic Consultants (Box 16)
      (re muscular grading)
    - Parke, Davis and Company (Box 16)
    - Physical therapists
      - General (Box 16)
      - 1954 (Box 16)
      - 1955 (Box 16)
      - 1956 (Box 16)
        (meeting of June 17-23)
    - Polio incidence (Box 16)
    - Priest Committee (Box 16)
      (U.S. Congress)
    - Salk, Jonas
      - Correspondence (Box 16)
      - Reprints and articles (Box 16)
      - Paper and correspondence re phenol red as indicator in titrating poliomyelitis virus (Box 16)
    - Seriological tests (Box 16)
    - Specialists and/or consulting physicians (Box 16)
    - Statistics
      - Absenteeism (Box 16)
      - Fatalities (Box 16)
      - In and out patients (Box 16)
      - Polio reported cases (Box 16)
    - Study Lab
      - Set-up (Box 16)
      - Procedures (Box 16)
      - Letters re participation (Box 16)
      - Summay replies (Box 16)
      - Name file
        - Bodian, David (Box 16)
        - Brown, Gordon (Box 16)
        - Coriell, Lewis L (Box 16)
        - Dalldorf, Gilbert (Box 16)
        - Enders, John F (Box 16)
        - Evans, Charles A (Box 16)
        - Fischer, Robert G (Box 17)
        - Fox, John P (Box 17)
        - Frisch, Arthur W (Box 17)
        - Gebhardt, Louis P (Box 17)
        - Kalter, Seymour S (Box 17)
        - Karzon, David (Box 17)
        - Larson, Carl L (Box 17)
        - Lennette, Edwin H (Box 17)
        - Melnick, Joseph L (Box 17)
        - Microbiological Associates (Box 17)
        - Rasmussen, Aaron (Box 17)
        - Robbins, Frederick C (Box 17)
        - Rustigan, Robert (Box 17)
        - Shaughnessy, Howard J (Box 17)
        - Schaeffer, Morris (Box 17)
        - Steigman, Alex J (Box 17)
        - Syverton, Jerome T (Box 17)
        - Wenner, Herbert A (Box 17)
      - Canada file
        - General (Box 17)
        - Canadian incidence (Box 17)
        - Defries, R.D (Box 17)
        - Wilt, J.C (Box 17)
        - Alberta (Box 17)
        - Manitoba (Box 17)
        - Nova Scotia (Box 17)
      - Finland file
        - Penttinen, Kari (Box 17)
          (State Serum Institute, Helsinki)
    - Summary data, 1 volume (Box 17)
      (placebo and observed study populations)
    - Technical Advisory Committee on Poliomyelitis
      - Topical
        - General (Box 17)
        - Regulations for poliomyelitis vaccine (Box 17)
        - Technical reports
          - June 1955 (Box 17)
          - October 1955 (Box 17)
          - November 1955 (Box 17)
        - Minimum requirements for polio virus vaccine (Box 18)
        - Monkey safety test for poliomyelitis (Box 18)
        - Potency testing of poliomyelitis vaccine (Box 18)
      - Meeting files
        - July-December 1955, 10 folders (Box 18)
        - January-November 1956, 7 folders (Box 19)
    - Vaccine
      - Allocation (Box 19)
      - Coding, labeling, packaging (Box 19)
      - Dummy packages (Box 19)
      - Inoculations (Box 19)
      - Lots (Box 19)
      - Manufacture and production (Box 19)
      - Placebo (Box 19)
      - Preliminary tabulation (Box 19)
      - Reactions (Box 19)
        (to vaccine)
      - Receipt of (Box 19)
      - Requests for immunization (Box 19)
      - Safety (Box 19)
      - Schedule (Box 19)
      - Selection of counties (Box 19)
      - Specifications and minimum requirements (Box 19)
      - Syringes (Box 19)
        (individual)
    - Virology (Box 20)
      - Hela cells (Box 20)
      - Medium #199 (Box 20)
      - Orphan viruses (Box 20)
      - Standard virus and serum (Box 20)
      - Tissue culture (Box 20)
      - Venules (Box 20)
      - Virus (Box 20)
        (live and dead)
  - Advisory Committee
    - Meeting files, 1954-1955; 5 folders (Box 20)
  - Lab consultant (Herbert A. Wenner), 1954-1956
    - Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 20)
    - Baltimore, February 1954 (Box 20)
    - Report on visitation to laboratories, May 1954 (Box 20)
    - Letter to laboratories re materials, June 1954 (Box 20)
    - Letter to laboratories re family studies and procedures, July 1954 (Box 20)
    - Questionnaires to laboratories, July 1954 (Box 20)
      (also re cross testing with sera)
    - Follow-up letter, September 1954 (Box 20)
    - Telegram, November 1954 (Box 20)
    - Telegram, January 1955 (Box 20)
    - Human reference sera, February 1955 (Box 20)
  - Statistical Division
    (Robert B. Voight/John Napier)
    - Topical
      - Analysis of referrals (Box 20)
      - Bureau of the Census (Box 20)
      - Correspondence, general, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Editing and coding (Box 20)
      - Organization (Box 20)
      - Personnel (Box 20)
      - Progress reports (Box 20)
      - Status reports, 4 folders (Box 20)
      - Weekly case reports (Box 20)
        (Dublin)
      - Work schedules (Box 20)
    - Chronological files (Box 21)
      (outgoing correspondence)
      - August 1954-June 1956, 9 volumes (Box 21)
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    (Chronological files, Thomas Francis file)
    - 1954-1957, 3 volumes, 1 folder (Box 21)
      - Work schedules (Box 21)
  - Final report and related
    - Evaluation of 1954 Field Trial of Poliomyelitis-Summary Report, April 12, 1955 (Box 22)
    - Evaluation of 1954 Field Trial of Poliomyelitis-Final Report, April, 1957 (Box 22)
    - Report of the Child Health Study, Survey Research Center of the University of Michigan (Box 22)
      (study of the ways in which participants in the polio vaccine study might differ from non-participants)
    - Original Material from Press Conference (Box 22)
    - Correspondence with state health agencies regarding effectiveness of poliomyelitis vaccine ud1b 1956 (Box 22)
  - Research
    - Lantern Slides with charts, graphs of labs studies etc. (Box 22)
    - Individual patient data files
      - Texas, Vermont, Virginia (Box 22)
        [Patient/client records restricted until July 01, 2055 ]
      - West Virginia, Wisconsin, Wyoming (Box 23)
    - Field Trial Registration Schedules(Microfilm) (Box 24)
      (arranged by state, with schools participating in the field tests, names of student, and other information germane to the tests)
      [Patient/client records restricted until July 01, 2055. See collection access statement for exceptions.]
- Armed Forces Epidemiological Board, 1938-1969; 10 linear feet
  The Armed Forces Epidemiological Board series is divided into two subseries; Presidents files and Commission on Influenza of the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board. The President's Files date from Francis' term as president of the board, 1958-1960. The Commission on Influenza records are in fact the official records of this agency. Established in 1941 with Francis as its head, the Commission on Influenza was headquartered within the School of Public Health. And when Francis stepped aside in 1955, his colleague Fred Davenport became director and served into the 1970s. The researcher interested in the work of the Commission and the Armed Forces Epidemiological Board should consult Davenport's papers at the library for related materials.
  - President's files, 1958-1960
    - Central Board (Box 28)
      - Memoranda for the files and notes on phone conversations on various subjects (Box 28)
      - Recommendations (Box 28)
      - Board members files
        - Bayne-Jones, Stanhope (Box 28)
        - Coggeshall, Lowell T (Box 28)
        - Dingle, John, 2 folders (Box 28)
          (include earlier Dingle papers, 1956-1957 when Dingle was president of the AFEB)
        - Francis, Thomas (Box 28)
        - Kern, Richard A (Box 28)
        - Loosli, Clayton (Box 28)
        - MacLeod, Colin (Box 28)
        - Shope, Richard E (Box 28)
        - Smith, Charles E (Box 28)
        - Wood, W. Barry (Box 28)
    - Fiscal and budget materials
      - Budget Planning summaries (Box 28)
      - Fiscal, 2 folders (Box 28)
      - Contract proposals (Box 28)
    - Meetings (board meetings and miscellaneous), 1958-1960; 14 folders (Box 28)
    - Military
      - Armed Forces Pest Control Board (Box 28)
      - Army Scientific Advisory Panel (Box 28)
      - Assistant Secretary of Defense (Box 28)
      - Babione, R.W (Box 28)
      - Benenson, A.S (Box 28)
      - Canadian Forces Medical Council (Box 28)
      - Cushing, E.H (Box 28)
      - Defense Science Board (Box 29)
      - Griffin, H.E (Box 29)
      - Hays, S.B. (Box 29)
        (Surgeon General)
      - Hullinghorst, R.L (Box 29)
      - Ley, H.L (Box 29)
      - Long, A.P (Box 29)
      - Military Medical Research Organizations (Box 29)
      - Office of Civil Defense and Mobilization (Box 29)
      - Rizzolo, John (Box 29)
        (executive secretary)
      - Timmerman, F.W (Box 29)
      - Vivona, Stefano (Box 29)
    - Radiation
      - General (Box 29)
      - Atomic Energy Commission (Box 29)
      - Contracts
        - Dingle, John (Box 29)
        - Ehrlich, R. (Box 29)
          (not granted)
        - Feller, A.E (Box 29)
        - Francis, Thomas (Box 29)
        - Havens, W. Paul (Box 29)
        - Nelson, Norton (Box 29)
        - Pillsbury, Donald M (Box 29)
        - Quilligan, J.J (Box 29)
        - Stetson, Chandler A (Box 29)
        - Wisseman, C.L (Box 29)
        - Wood, W. Barry (Box 29)
    - Policy and Special Studies
      - Consultants (Box 29)
      - Continuous cell lines (Box 29)
      - Human volunteers (Box 29)
      - Justification for the AFEB (Box 29)
      - Mental health (Box 29)
      - National Medical Research Unit (Box 29)
      - Nungester proposal (Box 29)
        (re pathogenesis of infectious diseases)
      - Penicillin (Box 29)
      - Poliomyelitis vaccine (Box 29)
        (4th dose)
      - Post regulations (Box 29)
        (re shipment of etiologic agents)
      - Protocols (Box 29)
      - Public information (Box 29)
      - Public information meeting, December 1959 (Box 29)
      - Sensitization and harmful effects of immunization (Box 29)
      - Serum repository-diagnostic reagents (Box 29)
      - Travel (Box 29)
      - Tropical medicine (Box 29)
    - Commissions (Box 30)
      - Accidental Trauma
        - General (Box 30)
        - Dunlap, Jack (Box 30)
      - Acute Respiratory Disease (Box 30)
      - Cutaneous Disease (Box 30)
      - Enteric Infections
        - General (Box 30)
        - Cholera studies (Box 30)
          (Kenneth Goodner)
        - Moan test (Box 30)
      - Epidemiological Survey
        - General (Box 30)
        - Dugway Proving Ground visit, 1959 (Box 30)
      - Environmental Hygiene (Box 30)
      - Immunization
        - General (Box 30)
        - Dengue study (Box 30)
          (Wisseman use of Japanese volunteers to test vaccine)
      - Influenza
        - General (Box 30)
        - Davenport, Fred M (Box 30)
        - Adenovirus vaccine (Box 30)
        - Adjuvant vaccines (Box 30)
        - Field studies, 1958-1959 (Box 30)
        - Fort Dix (Box 30)
        - Fort Ord, 2 folders (Box 30)
        - Influenza immunization program (Box 30)
        - Influenza virus vaccine (Box 30)
        - Kessler AFB (Box 30)
        - Lowry AFB (Box 30)
        - Meetings, 4 folders (Box 30)
        - Russian "Asian flu" vaccine (Box 30)
        - SAC pilot study (Box 30)
      - Parasitic Disease
        - General (Box 30)
        - Malaria research (Box 30)
      - Rickettsial Diseases
        - General (Box 31)
        - Q fever vaccine (Box 31)
        - Typhus vaccine (Box 31)
      - Streptococcal Diseases (Box 31)
      - Viral Infections
        - General (Box 31)
        - Havens, W. Paul (Box 31)
        - Paul, John (Box 31)
    - Board files
      - Meetings, 1960-1965; 14 folders (Box 31)
  - Commission on Influenza of the AFEB
    (Thomas Francis, Jr. was director of the Influenza Commission, 1941-1955)
    - Historical files
      - "History of The Commission on Influenza of the Board for the Investigation and Control of Influenza and other Epidemic Diseases in the Army February 1941-December 1945" (Box 32)
        (unpublished 86 page mss written by Thomas Francis, Jr)
    - Alphabetical file, 1941-1947
      (some files date forward to 1950, file letters A-H missing)
      - I-J; individual file folders include (Box 32)
        - Influenza vaccination studies, 1943-1945
          - California, 2 folders (Box 32)
          - Chicago, 2 folders (Box 32)
            (study done in conjunction with Wellston, Michigan; see also material in Wellston, Michigan folders)
          - Cornell, 5 folders (Box 32)
          - Iowa (Box 32)
          - Michigan (Box 32)
          - Minnesota (Box 32)
          - Utah (Box 32)
            (Camp Kerns)
          - Various
            - Hirst, George K (Box 32)
            - Rickard/Sawyer correspondence (Box 32)
            - Final reports (Box 32)
              (and correspondence about)
        - Jaundice/Hepatitis studies (Box 32)
          (.5 lin. ft. not further described)
      - J-P; individual file folders include (Box 33)
        - Jaundice/Hepatitis studies (Box 33)
          (.2 lin. ft. not further described)
        - Lederle Laboratories (Box 33)
        - MacLeod, Colin M (Box 33)
        - Masks (Box 33)
          (information and correspondence about)
        - Meetings (Epidemiological Board), 1941-1950 (Box 33)
        - MidPac investigation, 1945 (Box 33)
          (notes, data, report)
        - Patents (Box 33)
        - Personnel, 2 folders (Box 33)
        - Proposed studies and budgets (Box 33)
        - Proposed materials and equipment (Box 33)
        - Priorities (Box 33)
        - Publications (Box 33)
      - P-Z; individual file folders include (Box 34)
        - Puerto Rico trip, 1944 (Box 34)
        - Reports of studies undera the Influenza Commission done by members of the Commission, 1943-1946; 4 folders (Box 34)
        - Respiratory disease outbreak: Chanute & Scott Fields, February 1947 (Box 34)
          (reported by Jonas Salk)
        - Respiratory Disease-Camp Custer, 1942-1944 (Box 34)
        - Salk, Jonas, 2 folders (Box 34)
        - Sioux Falls, South Dakota, 1943 (Box 34)
        - Stanley, W.M.
          (Rockefeller Foundation)
          - Correspondence (Box 34)
          - Vaccine-stability (Box 34)
          - Vaccine-toxicity (Box 34)
        - Wellston, Michigan experiment, 2 folders (Box 34)
    - Alphabetical file, 1948-1950
      (some files date back to 1941)
      - A-M; individual file folders include (Box 35)
        - Andrewes, C.H. (Box 35)
          (International Strain Study Center)
        - Bauer, Frank L (Box 35)
        - Contracts, 1941-1950; 10 folders (Box 35)
        - Fourth Medical Field Laboratory-European Command (Box 35)
        - Influenza, 1947-1950; 5 folders (Box 35)
        - Lederle Laboratories (Box 35)
        - MacLeod, Colin M (Box 35)
        - Magill, T.P
          - Correspondence (Box 35)
          - Strain Study Center form letters (Box 35)
          - Re chairmanship of committee to arrive at a standardization of serological procedure (Box 35)
      - M-Z; individual file folders include (Box 36)
        - Meetings and conferences, 6 folders (Box 36)
        - Publications by commission members (Box 36)
        - Reports, 4 folders (Box 36)
          (quarterly, annual, etc)
        - Salk, Jonas (Box 36)
        - Shope, R.E. (Box 36)
          (re oti strain)
        - Vaccination programs
          - 1946
            - Michigan (Box 36)
            - Minnesota (Box 36)
            - U.S. Army (Box 36)
          - 1947
            - Commission (Box 36)
            - Salk, Jonas (Box 36)
          - 1948-1949
            - Michigan (Box 36)
            - Jonas Salk at Fort Dix (Box 36)
            - Gordon Meikeljohn at Fort Ord (Box 36)
          - Hall's final summary for influenza, 1947-1948 (Box 36)
          - Potency tests (Box 36)
          - Procurement, 1948 (Box 36)
          - Protocols concerning antigenicity, 1948 (Box 36)
          - Specifications and requirements, 1944-1947 (Box 36)
        - World Health Organization (Box 36)
          (Influenza Information Center)
    - Alphabetical file, 1951-1955
      (NOTE: This alphabetical series continues in the papers of Fred Davenport who succeeded Francis as director of the Commission on Influenza)
      - A-R; individual file folders include (Box 37)
        - Alaska (Box 37)
          (exhumation of bodies from 1918 epidemic)
        - History of Preventive Medicine, U.S. Army Medical Department, World War II (Box 37)
          (section on influenza)
        - Influenza current, 4 folders (Box 37)
        - Influenza-gamma globulin (Box 37)
        - Lennette, Edwin
          - General (Box 37)
          - Adenoviruses (Box 37)
        - MacLeod, Colin (Box 37)
        - Magill, T.P.-Strain Study Center (Box 37)
        - Meiklejohn, Gordon (Box 37)
        - Meetings, 9 folders (Box 37)
        - Monovalent studies (Box 37)
        - News releases (Box 37)
        - Publications (Box 37)
        - Rapalski, A.J (Box 37)
        - Reports (Box 37)
          (semi-annual and quarterly)
      - R-Z; individual file folders include (Box 38)
        - Respiratory disease rates-Army (Box 38)
        - Rose, Harry M (Box 38)
        - Salk, Jonas (Box 38)
        - Sampson Air Force Base Study, 3 folders (Box 38)
        - Vaccine, 5 folders (Box 38)
        - World Health Organization-Influenza Information Center (Box 38)
    - Meeting files, 1959-1966; 11 folders
      (During and following his presidency of the AFEB, Thomas Francis, Jr. continued to serve as a member and a responsible investigator of the Commission on Influenza; these are the files from this period in his career)
      - Meeting files (Box 38)
    - Responsible investigator reports
      - Reports (Box 38)
- Organizations, 1938-1969; 22 linear feet
  Organizations, 1939-1969 (2 linear feet). The largest series in the collection, Organizations, is an amalgam of separate groupings of records pertaining to Thomas Francis' participation in professional, private, and governmental organizations and agencies. The size of the subseries vary considerably depending upon the level of his involvement and the period of time in which he was active. Where Francis was director or heavily involved, the amount of records is extensive, substantive, and important to any study of Francis' career. Where his participation was less direct, the organization files consist of professional exchanges, conferences and meetings, papers and publications, and advice and counsel sought and exchanged. The Organization series is arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization and thereafter topically.
  Among the most significant organizational files are those of the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, which was a prime sponsor of Francis' work on the polio vaccine tests.
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1960 (Box 25)
  - American Academy of Microbiology, 1957-1961; 1967 (Box 25)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science, 1950-1957 (Box 25)
  - American Association of Immunologists
    - 1948-1950 (Box 25)
    - 1951-1955 (Box 25)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 25)
    - 1961-1969 (Box 25)
    - Journal of Immunology
      - 1940-1948 (Box 25)
      - 1949-1950 (Box 25)
      - 1951-1957 (Box 25)
  - American Bacteriologists, Society of
    - 1939-1945 (Box 25)
    - 1946 (Box 25)
    - January-March 1947 (Box 25)
    - April-December 1947 (Box 25)
    - 1948 (Box 25)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 25)
    - 1951-1959 (Box 25)
    - Bacteriological Reviews, 1951-1954 (Box 25)
      (continued as American Society for Microbiology)
    - Government Research panel, 1949-1950 (Box 25)
  - American Board of Preventive Medicine and Public Health, 1949-1954 (Box 25)
    (formerly Interim Board for Preventive Medicine)
  - American College of Physicians, 1938-1969 (Box 25)
    (scattered dates)
  - American College of Preventive Medicine, 1956-1957 (Box 25)
  - American Epidemiological Society
    - 1943-1948 (Box 25)
    - 1949-1950 (Box 25)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 25)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 25)
    - 1964-1968 (Box 25)
  - American Medical Association